在科罗拉多州的群山深处，
Tucked away in the mountains of Colorado
藏着一项美国最与众不同的建设工程。
is one of America's most unusual construction projects.
这里就是格罗斯水库，
This here is the Gross Reservoir,
半个多世纪以来，
which has been supplying the city of Denver with much of its water
它一直是丹佛市主要的水源供应地。
for more than half a century.
但水还是不够用。
But not enough water.
系统需求前所未有地高涨，
With more demand on the system than ever before,
自然灾害的威胁也与日俱增，
and natural disasters becoming increasingly likely,
这座人工湖如今必须大幅扩容。
this man-made lake now needs to be a lot bigger.
常识告诉我们，
It's reasonable to assume
水库的容量取决于拦截它的大坝，
a reservoir can only be as big as the dam that created it,
这就是为什么工程团队
which is why teams here are having to pull off
必须先完成一项罕见而艰难的任务。
a rare and difficult task first.
他们要在原有大坝的基础上，再建一座新坝。
They're expanding the dam itself by building a new one on top of it.
>> 这真的是世界上第一次
>> Well, this is really the first time
将一座重力坝改造成拱坝。
that a gravity dam is being transformed into an arch dam.
前所未有，极其复杂。
And it's incredibly unique, incredibly complex.
然而，就在工程即将收尾之际，
And yet, with the finish line now in sight,
一个棘手的难题却迟迟无法解决。
there's a serious problem that won't go away.
这个问题已经让这项宏大工程陷入了停摆。
One that's already seen this gigantic scheme stopped in its tracks.
说到科罗拉多，你脑海中浮现的大概就是这样的画面。
Think Colorado, and you'll probably imagine something like this.
丹佛郊外便是落基山脉的起点，
Just outside Denver is where the Rocky Mountains begin
这里拥有丰沛的水资源。
and where a great deal of water can be found.
湖泊、水库、科罗拉多河及其支流，触手可及。
There are lakes, reservoirs, the Colorado River, and its tributaries, all within reach.
如果你向往宁静的生活，这里再合适不过。
It's a good place to be if you like the quiet life.
只有这处特定的地点例外——
Except that is for this particular site,
近年来，这里已经成了一个热火朝天的工地。
which has become a hive of activity in recent years.
上世纪五十年代，
Back in the 1950s,
为了服务丹佛都会区，这里修建了一座大型重力坝。
a large gravity dam was built here to serve the Denver metropolitan area.
随着人口不断增长，
Due to its rising population,
城市需要开辟新的水源，
the city needed a new water source
来满足日益增加的用水需求。
to keep up with increased demand and resources.
格罗斯水库就此诞生。
And so the gross reservoir was born.
不过，水库可不会自己蓄满水的。
But reservoirs don't just fill up on their own.
当然，首先得建起那道混凝土巨墙——格罗斯大坝。
Of course, a massive wall of concrete, the Gross Dam, had to be built first.
它主要拦截来自弗雷泽河的水，
It would capture water coming in mainly from the Fraser River,
弗雷泽河经由马菲特隧道汇入雄伟的科罗拉多河。
which joins onto the mighty Colorado River via the Muffet Tunnel.
好，在继续之前，
Okay, but before we move on,
有件事我实在忍不住要问——
and because I just can't ignore anymore,
为什么叫"格罗斯"水库？
why is it called the Gross Reservoir?
>> 格罗斯。
>> Gross.
不，这个名字既不是因为它让人恶心，
Well, no, it's not because it's disgusting or because of its size,
也不是因为它的规模——虽然确实相当可观。
which is pretty substantial.
>> 你这傻瓜。
>> Freaking idiot.
>> 这个名字其实来自德怀特·D·格罗斯，
>> It's actually named after Dwight D. Gross,
他曾是丹佛水务局的首席工程师。
who was the former chief engineer of Denver Water.
丹佛水务局是拥有并运营这座水库和大坝的公共事业机构。
That's the utility company that owns and operates both the reservoir and the dam.
不好意思扫了大家的兴，但现在你们都知道了。
Sorry to ruin the fun, but obviously you now know.
水库蓄满时，可容纳四万两千英亩英尺，
When full, the reservoir is capable of holding 42,000 acre feet,
约合五千两百万立方米的水。
around 52 million cubic m of water.
几十年来，这个容量一直够用，
And for decades that was absolutely fine
直到2020年，丹佛水务局获批
until 2020 when Denver Water got permission to expand the reservoir
将大坝再加高逾一百英尺，以扩大水库容量。
by making the dam even bigger by over 100 ft.
届时，库容将增至约十一万九千英亩英尺，
That would see capacity increase almost threefold to 119,000 acret
接近一亿五千万立方米，
or nearly 150 million cub m
足以每年为七万两千户家庭供水。
enough to supply 72,000 homes with water every year.
这由此催生了一项庞大工程——
What that led to is a ginormous project
在一座三百四十英尺高的大坝上，
to build a 131 ft dam raise
再加建一百三十一英尺。
on top of a 340 ft tall dam.
>> 杰夫·马丁是丹佛水务局负责人，
>> Jeff Martin leads the team at Denver Water,
全面统筹这一项目，从方案构思到竣工交付，一手掌舵。
responsible for the entire program from concept right through to completion.
>> 在2025年建造一座四百七十一英尺高的混凝土大坝，
>> Building a 471 ft concrete dam in 2025
挑战重重，方方面面都不简单。
is a challenging endeavor on a number of fronts.
放眼全球，这个体量都是首屈一指的，
That is big under any standards throughout the world
而我们所做的事情极为罕见——
and it's extremely rare what we're tackling
这一切，只是为了给丹佛地区提供安全可靠的水资源保障。
really just to provide a secure water future to the Denver area.
为何要保障供水安全？
Why does it need securing?
多年来，丹佛及邻近的博尔德县
Well, because over the years Denver and neighboring Boulder County
越来越容易受到各类涉水灾害的威胁。
have become increasingly vulnerable to water related disasters.
>> 本周末，科罗拉多州博尔德南部发生野火，数千人被迫紧急疏散。
>> Well, a wildfire south of Boulder, Colorado this weekend forced thousands to flee.
科罗拉多州各地旱情持续。
the drought picture across Colorado.
这是近年来最为严峻的旱灾形势。
The worst drought situation that we've had in several years.
>> 该地区已出现大范围洪涝灾害，
>> There is widespread flood activity across the area.
紧急救援人员敦促所有人立即转移至高处避险。
Emergency officials are urging you to seek higher ground immediately.
>> 科罗拉多可不只有白雪皑皑的山峰。
>> There's more than just snowy mountains in Colorado.
这里可以极度酷热干燥，也可以大雨滂沱。
It can get very hot, dry, and also pretty wet here, too.
2002年，该地区遭遇了异常严重的旱灾，
2002 saw an unusually serious drought along with the Haymon fire,
同年的海蒙山火更是烧毁了逾百栋房屋。
which destroyed well over a 100 homes.
因此，当灾难来临时，
So having more water available to deal with such problems
拥有更充足的水资源来应对这些问题，就显得顺理成章了。
if and when they occur starts to make sense.
人口增长也没有停下来的迹象。
Population growth doesn't show any signs of stopping either.
2020年，丹佛水务局宣布，日用水人口已攀升至一百五十万，
In 2020, Denver Water announced that daily users had risen to 1.5 million people,
比四年前增加了整整十万人。
100,000 higher than just 4 years before.
供水系统在水资源储备的地域分布上也存在明显失衡。
There's a pretty big imbalance with where it stores its water as well.
九成的水储存在丹佛南部的水库中，
90% of it is held in reservoirs to the south of Denver
北部（包括格罗斯大坝所在地）仅占一成。
with the other 10% to the north where the gross dam is.
尽管听起来难以置信，
But despite how it might sound,
但扩建这座颇具气势的基础设施，
expanding this rather imposing piece of infrastructure
其实并非什么新鲜想法。
is actually not a new idea.
事实上，这几乎是从一开始就埋下的伏笔。
In fact, it was kind of the plan right from the beginning.
当初建造这座大坝时，就预留了日后加高的可能，
You see, the dam was constructed with the intention of being raised
一旦有此必要，随时可以实施——
at least once should that become necessary in the future,
而现在，时机显然已经成熟。
which it clearly has.
稍后，我们会详细介绍工程团队
So, in a minute, we're going to come on to how teams here
是如何推进这一
have actually been delivering on a scheme
旨在让城市长期高效运转的方案的。
that's designed to keep a city flowing efficiently for years to come.
不过在这之前，
But before we do that,
我想聊聊另一件事——
I want to talk to you about something
它同样是为了让建设这类项目的企业
that's designed to do the same for the businesses
能够高效运转。
who build projects like this.
这些企业的运营可以非常复杂。
The way these businesses operate can be very complex.
相信我，他们最不需要的，
And trust me, the last thing they need is more stress
就是在资金管理上再添麻烦。
when it comes to payments.
销售、交易、客户、业绩、库存……
Sales, transactions, customers, performance, inventory.
这些往往靠人工操作，或者用一堆互不相通的工具来处理。
They're often done manually or using tools that are disconnected.
这不仅难以管理，更直接侵蚀利润——
This isn't only hard to manage, it hurts profits,
这正是 Sky OS 登场的原因。
which is where Sky OS comes in.
它是一套专为行业打造的操作系统，
It's a purpose-built operating system
将所有流程整合到一个互联平台，
that brings all those processes together into one connected platform,
兼顾效率与全局掌控。
giving you both speed and visibility.
专为建筑行业设计，
Designed for the construction industry,
让业主对每一笔流经企业的资金了如指掌。
it gives owners control over every dollar that moves through their business.
可以把它理解成一座"大坝"——
In fact, it works a little bit like a DAN,
只不过它拦截的不是水，而是利润的流失；
except instead of retaining water and dictating how it's used,
它管控的不是水流，而是成本的走向。
Skyos lets you retain profits and manage costs.
实时洞察与业绩看板，
Real-time insights and performance dashboards show you where profits are earned
清晰呈现每一笔盈亏的来源。
and where money is lost.
产品与库存工具让每一项材料、税款和折扣都井井有条；
Product and inventory tools keep every material, tax, and discount organized,
为每位客户量身定制的全托管账户，
while fully managed accounts can be easily made for each client,
彻底告别繁琐的纸质流程。
meaning no more paper trails.
凭借智能化的自动付款优化功能，
And because it's automated with intelligence payment optimization,
它已被证实可将利润提升多达20%。
it's proven to increase profits by up to 20%.
点击下方链接，
You can see how Skyos is giving billions back
了解 Sky OS 如何为建筑行业创造数十亿价值，重塑数字化基础。
and rebuilding the digital foundation of the construction industry at the link below.
好了，让我们回到科罗拉多，
Now, let's get back over to Colorado
看看大坝到底是怎么"长高"的。
and see how on earth you raise a dam.
思路很直接，就是在现有大坝上增加更多混凝土，
The idea is obviously to add more concrete to the existing dam,
但不只是往上堆。
but not just on top.
他们还需要加固朝南侧，也就是背水坡，
They're having to build up the southacing or dry side as well
以确保整体稳定性。
to help maintain stability.
为此，
To achieve this,
工程团队从地面一路向上，
118 concrete steps are being constructed from the ground
修建了一百一十八级混凝土台阶，直抵新坝顶部。
right up the top of the new dam.
每级台阶高四英尺，相对于下方台阶向后退缩两英尺。
Each one is 4 ft high and set back 2 ft from the step underneath.
之后再铺设坝顶，
Then the crest or tip goes on,
安装控制楼、电气设施、护栏，以及横跨溢洪道的桥梁。
followed by a control building, electronics, railing, and bridge across the spillway.
工程于2022年动工，
Construction began in 2022,
到2025年6月，施工已推进至原坝顶高度——
and by June 2025, workers had reached the height of the original dam,
海拔逾七千英尺。
more than 7,000 ft above sea level.
在建造方式上，
As for the method used to create these steps,
丹佛水务局选择了与当年建造原坝截然不同的方案。
Denver Water has chosen a different approach to the original dam's builders.
建造混凝土大坝有两种方法。
There's two ways to make a concrete dam.
一种是我们所说的常规混凝土工艺。
One is with what we call conventional concrete.
原坝就是用这种方式建造的。
That's how the original dam was built.
基本上是把混凝土分成五十英尺的块段，一层层向上浇筑。
And it's basically built in 50 ft blocks all the way up.
胡佛坝
And uh just like Hoover was
和世界上许多其他著名混凝土大坝，
and some of the other iconic concrete dams
当年都是这么建起来的。
uh throughout the world were done.
上世纪八十年代，一种新工艺因技术创新而问世。
In the 1980s, a new uh method came into existence through innovation.
这就是碾压混凝土工艺。
It's called roller compacted concrete.
首先，混凝土由自卸车运入，
First, the concrete is brought in by dump truck,
直接卸料倒在作业面上。
which well dumps the material on top of the surface.
接着由推土机将其摊铺开来，
Next, it's spread by a bulldozer
再用光面振动压路机进行碾压压实。
before being rolled and compressed by a smooth drum compactor.
混凝土在现场拌制，由岩石、水泥、粉煤灰和水混合而成。
The concrete's made on sights, a mixture of rocks, cement, fly ash, and water.
尽管此前也有其他大坝经历过加高，
While other dams have been raised before,
但这是全球迄今为止规模最大的碾压混凝土大坝加高工程。
this is the largest one in the world to be done using RCC.
因为原坝已有超过六十万立方码的常规混凝土，
because we had over 600,000 yards of conventional concrete
而我们要在此基础上覆盖超过七十万立方码的
and we're going to overlay that with over 700,000 yards
新碾压混凝土。
of new roller compacted concrete.
配合比设计本身、浇筑过程中必须保持的温度控制，
The mix design itself, temperatures that it had to maintain during placement
以及新混凝土与旧坝体的接合方式——
and how it was placed against the old dam
这些都是至关重要的细节，
were all extremely critical details on making sure
确保新旧坝体能够合为一体，作为一座完整的坝发挥作用。
that this dam behaves as one dam going forward.
碾压混凝土的水化热更低，
This choice of material offers lower curing temperatures,
意味着它的凝结时间比普通混凝土更短。
meaning it doesn't take as long to set as regular concrete.
与此同时，它的内含碳排放量更少，也更不容易开裂。
Embodied carbon is reduced as well, and it's less likely to crack.
一切似乎都按计划推进，然而……
So, everything appears to be going to plan, except
>> 一名联邦地区法院法官做出裁决，给这一项目带来了巨大打击——
>> a federal district court judge has dealt an expensive setback at least,
代价极为高昂，甚至可能让整个工程就此画上句号。
and possibly an end to the project.
2025年4月，一纸法院禁令让项目全面停工。
In April 2025, all construction on the project was put on hold following a court injunction.
一名美国地区法院法官裁定，
A US district judge ruled in favor of environmental groups
多年来持续反对该扩建计划的环保团体胜诉。
who've been campaigning against this expansion for years.
这些团体包括护水者联盟、塞拉俱乐部和拯救科罗拉多组织。
They include the Water Keeper Alliance, Sierra Club, and Save the Colorado.
他们认为，扩建后的大型水库
They believe the new larger reservoir will have a negative effect
将对整个科罗拉多河水系以及周边居民产生负面影响。
on the wider Colorado River water system as well as nearby residents.
这个项目将从科罗拉多河抽取更多水资源，而这条河正处于危机之中。
This project would drain more water out of the Colorado River. It's in crisis mode.
美国西南部各州都在想方设法
Um and all the states in the southwest United States
减少对科罗拉多河的用水，
are trying to decide how to use less Colorado River water
而这个项目反其道而行之，只会用得更多。
and this one would use more.
其次，这将是博尔德县有史以来规模最大的建设工程，
The second reason is that they would it would be
而且已然成真。
and it has been the biggest construction project in Boulder County history.
周边大约有一千户居民。
There's about a thousand houses up and around the area.
这场没日没夜的施工，对那些生活在其中的人来说，简直是一场噩梦。
It's been an extraordinary nightmare for those people living through this 24/7 construction process.
更令人信服的是，
Adding credence to these claims,
有消息表明，负责审批许可的美国陆军工程兵团，
it emerged the US Army Corps of Engineers, which supplied the permits,
在批准项目时，并未充分评估其对环境的全面影响。
didn't factor in the full environmental impact when it approved the project.
法官认为，针对此次扩建的可行替代方案并未得到充分论证，
According to the judge, viable alternatives to this expansion were not properly addressed,
这让加里和他的团队在法庭上取得了一场颇为出人意料的胜利——
which led to a somewhat unlikely win for Gary and his team in court
毕竟，他们的对手分量不轻。
when you consider who they were up against.
这无疑是一场法律上的胜利，
It certainly was a legal victory
堪称真正的"以弱胜强"。
and it certainly is a David versus Goliath phenomenon.
我们是一个小小的机构，
We're a tiny organization
而对方是美国西南部最大的供水机构之一。
and they're one of the biggest water providers in the Southwest United States.
他们有一支实力雄厚、高度专业的律师团队。
Um, and they do have a extremely big and high-powered law firm.
我们则是一支精干高效的护河队伍。
We're a lean, mean river saving machine.
我认为地区法院的判决结果站在了我们这一边。
I think the outcome of the district court really worked on our behalf.
>> 但这只是一次短暂的中断。
>> But it was only a temporary port.
仅仅一个月后，法官便做出了180度转变——
Just a month later, the judge did a U-turn
丹佛水务局主张，若大坝工程烂尾，可能引发洪水等严重后果，法官对此予以采信。
after claims from Denver Water
that leaving the dam unfinished could lead to serious consequences like flooding.
施工就此得以恢复。
That meant construction could continue.
但一个相当棘手的问题依然悬而未决。
But there was still one pretty big issue remaining.
尽管获准继续施工，当局却尚未批准扩建后的水库蓄水——
Although they got the green light to carry out the works,
至少目前还没有。
permission was not given to actually fill the expanded reservoir,
at least not yet.
水库蓄水预计需要约五年时间，
The process of filling the reservoir is expected to take around 5 years,
但何时能够启动，乃至能否启动，目前仍是未知数。
but we still don't know when or even if that can happen.
新的许可证需要重新审批，
New permits would need to be signed first,
而由于陆军工程兵团曾犯下严重且大量的程序性错误，审批过程注定不会一帆风顺。
but because the Army Corps of Engineers made extensive and serious errors,
it's unlikely to be straightforward.
眼下存在一种可能——这一切的努力，最终都将付诸东流。
So, there's a chance that all of this could be for nothing.
不过，让我们先暂且退一步，
Okay, but let's rewind a bit and dig a little deeper
深入了解一下环保人士究竟对哪些问题感到不满。
into what exactly it is that campaigners are unhappy about.
这座大坝都已经在这里矗立了约七十年，
If this dam's already been here for about 70 years,
把它稍微扩建一下，又有什么问题呢？
then what's wrong with just making it a bit bigger?
这总比在别处新建一座大坝和水库要好得多吧？
Surely, that's better than building an entirely new dam and reservoir somewhere else.
这正是丹佛水务局为将影响降至最低而采取的缓解措施之一——
This is one of the mitigation measures
否则，对当地环境的冲击可能更为巨大。
that Denver Water has put in place
to limit what could otherwise be a much larger impact on the local environment.
在水库中储存更多水，也可以将更多水引入邻近的溪流，
By storing extra water in the reservoir,
从而改善鱼类栖息环境。
they can also direct more of it into the adjacent creek,
improving fish habitats.
他们还在规划新建湿地，并划定保护区，
They're also introducing new wetlands and preserving other areas
以弥补此类项目不可避免造成的林地损失。
to offset some of the deforestation
that has to happen on a project like this.
大约二十万棵树木将被移除——
Around 200,000 trees are being removed,
当大量土地被淹没、水质又必须严格维护时，这几乎是无法回避的代价。
which is sort of inevitable when so much land is being inundated
and water quality has to be maintained.
面对这样的工程，唯一的应对之道就是秉持环境保护的理念，
There's only one way to tackle a project like this
全面评估项目对环境带来的各类影响。
and that's with a culture of environmental stewardship
and making sure that we're fully analyzing the impacts from the project.
我们已经采取了大量不同的缓解措施，
We've done a lot of different mitigation to make sure
力求最终实现对科罗拉多州净环境效益的正向贡献。
that in the end that this is a net environmental benefit
to the state of Colorado.
>> 话虽如此，加里却并不买账。
>> That might be so, but Gary isn't convinced.
他认为，这些大坝造成的影响实在太过严重，不仅波及当地，
He believes the impact of these dams is just too great,
更冲击整个科罗拉多河流域。
not just on the local area, but on the whole Colorado River basin.
大坝会扼杀河流。
Dams kill rivers.
这就是大坝的本质。
That's what dams do.
它们阻断河流。
They block a river.
如果是水电大坝，它们不仅阻断河流，
Uh if it's a hydropower dam, they block a river
还会彻底改变水流的走向与节奏。
and completely changed the flow of the water in the river.
气候科学家指出，干旱与气候变化已导致整个科罗拉多河的流量下降了约20%。
The climate scientists claim drought and climate change have lowered the flow
in the entire Colorado River around 20%.
相较于原有的流量，这条河已遭受重创。
From its original flow and so the river has already been devastated.
而这一工程只会让情况更加恶化，这就是我们坚决反对的原因。
This will make it worse and that's why we're opposing it.
>> 还有一个不得不面对的问题——资金。
>> Then there's the cost of all this.
2021年项目获批时，预算定为五亿三千一百万美元。
When the project gained approval in 2021,
the price was set at $531 million.
这也是目前流传最广的数字。
And that remains the most widely reported figure.
但如果将始料未及的法律诉讼费用，以及现在需要重新申请的新许可证成本也纳入考量，
But when you factor in the unexpected legal costs and the new permits
这个数字很可能还会继续攀升。
that now need to be done,
there's a good chance that number's going to rise.
至于这笔钱从哪里来，与许多美国基础设施项目不同，
As for where that money comes from,
这里用的不是纳税人的钱。
unlike a lot of American infrastructure projects,
it won't be tax dollars.
丹佛水务局的资金完全来自用水费缴费者缴纳的水费、新用户接入收费，
Denver Water is funded entirely by rate payers,
以及可再生能源的销售收入。
fees for connecting new customers,
and the sale of renewable energy.
格罗斯大坝自2007年起便配套建有自己的水电站。
Gross Dam has been home to its own hydro plant since 2007.
尽管公司经历了重重波折，
Despite the problems the company's faced,
水库的这次重大扩建也已离竣工不远了。
their reservoir's latest upgrade isn't too far from the end.
他们计划在2026年完成坝顶封顶，
2026 is when they plan to top out on the dam
并建成溢洪道和配套建筑。
and finish the spillway and supporting buildings.
再过一年，如果届时获得许可，
A year later, it'll be time to start filling the reservoir,
蓄水工程便可正式启动。
assuming they've been cleared to do so.
和许多历经重大波折的建设项目一样，格罗斯水库扩建工程如今因"出了什么问题"而广为人知，
Like so many other construction projects that have had some major issues,
远超"做成了什么"。
the gross reservoir expansion is becoming known more for what's gone wrong
than what's gone right.
但在那些挫折与环保隐忧之外，
But while the setbacks and environmental concerns shouldn't be overlooked,
这里所追求的目标同样值得被认可与肯定。
what they're trying to achieve here deserves recognition, too.
这究竟是对丹佛、博尔德县，还是对整个科罗拉多州的一件好事，
Whether or not this is a good thing for Denver, Boulder County,
显然还存在争议。
or the whole of Colorado is clearly a contested topic.
但有一点无可否认——这是一项真正意义上"更上一层楼"的建筑壮举。
But what can't be denied is that this is a feat of construction
that truly raises the bar.
本视频由 Sky Systems 赞助。
This video was sponsored by Sky Systems.
别忘了点击下方链接，了解 Sky OS 如何助力您的业务腾飞。
Don't forget to go and check out how Skyos can help your business
at the link below.
一如既往，各位，如果你觉得这期视频够"坝"劲，
And as always guys, if you thought this video was damn good
想要更多来自这个顶级建筑频道的精彩内容，记得订阅我们。
and you want to get more from the definitive video channel for construction,
make damn sure you subscribe.